Guide to the Thomas Campbell Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Thomas Campbell papers
1821-1846
OSB MSS 106
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.04
(3 boxes)
Correspondence, writings, commonplace books, and other papers related to Thomas Campbell. Correspondence consists of a copy of a letter from Thomas Jefferson to Campbell. Campbell's writings include drafts of essays and biographies included in Specimens of British Poets; additional biographies of British poets; lectures on English poetry and drama; an annotated copy of The Poetical Works of Thomas Campbell; English history timelines, 872-1189; and research notes on English history and literature. Two commonplace books include correspondence to and from Campbell; "Reminiscences of the Poet" (1837-44) transcribed from a diary kept by Roylance Child; "Campbell's School Poems and Translations, 1787-1792;" poems by Campbell, possibly transcribed by William Beattie; and letters to Beattie from James Wingate regarding copies of Campbell's poems. Also includes manuscript copies of poems by various 17th and 18th century British poets. Other papers include a summons in a case of "Frederick Campbell Stewart, Esc. of Ascog, against Ferdinand S. Campbell and the other Heirs of Entail to the Estates of Ascog."
Campbell, Thomas, 1777-1844
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased at Sotheby's, 1966.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
THOMAS CAMPBELL (1777-1844)
Thomas Campbell (1777-1844) was born in Glasgow on July 27, 1777, to Alexander and Margaret Campbell. He attended Glasgow University from 1791-95. He married Matilda Sinclair (ca. 1780-1828) on October 10, 1803, and had two sons.
A poet, Campbell published his most successful and popular poem, The Pleasures of Hope (Edinburgh: Mundell & Son) in 1799. Other major works include the war poems "Hohenlinden," "The Battle of the Baltic," and "Ye Mariners of England", as well as Gertrude of Wyoming (London: Longman, Hurst, Rees, and Orme, 1809) and Theodric (London: Longman, Hurst, Rees, Orme, Brown, and Green, 1824). Other writings include The Annals of Great Britain (Edinburgh: Mundell, Doig & Stevenson, 1807) and Specimens of the British Poets (London: John Murray, 1819).
Campbell served as editor of New Monthly Magazine (London: Henry Colburn, 1821-30) and was a successful public lecturer. He died in Boulogne on June 15, 1844, and was buried in Westminster Abbey on July 3.
Scope and Contents
The Thomas Campbell Papers consist of correspondence, writings, commonplace books and other papers related to Thomas Campbell (1777-1844), a Scottish poet active during the late eighteenth and early nineteenth centuries. The papers span the years 1821-1846, and are housed in three boxes. They are organized into five series: Correspondence, Writings, Commonplace Books, Writings of Others, and Other Papers.
Series I, Correspondence, consists of an undated copy of a Thomas Jefferson letter (April 29, 1825) to Thomas Campbell, in which Jefferson answers Campbell's request on behalf of a Mr. Rose for advice on relocating to Virginia. Additional Thomas Campbell correspondence can be found in Series III, Commonplace Books.
Series II, Writings spans folders 2-27 and consists of writings of Thomas Campbell, 1821-39, arranged chronologically by date of publication. Writings consist of published and unpublished materials, including biographies of English poets, lectures on poetry and drama, poems by Campbell, English history timelines and research notes, and unidentified writings.
Papers related to Campbell's Specimens of the British Poets (London: John Murray, 1819) include manuscript drafts of portions of the introductory "Essay on English Poetry" and drafts of biographical essays on many English poets, including Geoffrey Chaucer, Edmund Spencer, John Milton, John Dryden, Alexander Pope, William Cowper, Robert Burns, and others. The series also includes manuscript biographies of poets not included in Specimens of British Poets.
Lectures include manuscript drafts of "Lectures on Poetry" and "Lectures on Drama," as well as a printed version of "Lectures on Poetry" from The New Monthly Magazine (London: Henry Colburn, 1821), which is interleaved into a notebook. Poems consist of an annotated copy of The Poetical Works of Thomas Campbell (London: Edward Moxon, Dover Street, 1839), which is interleaved into a notebook.
Additional writings include timelines of English history, 872-1189, research notes on several published works including Sharon Turner's The History of the Anglo-Saxons from the Earliest Period to the Norman Conquest and George Ellis's Specimens of Early English Metrical Romance, and unidentified writings.
Series III, Commonplace Books, consists of two volumes, ca. 1846, in folders 28-29. A commonplace book with the title "Campbell. Poems." includes "Reminiscences of the Poet" (1837-44) transcribed from a diary kept by Roylance Child; Thomas Campbell correspondence (ca. 1795-1841), including some mansucript copies and consisting of letters to and/or from the following correspondents: Thomas Moore, H. Brougham, Archibald Campbell (b. 1781, Campbell's brother), Archibald Campbell (Campbell's nephew), Margaret Campbell (Campbell's mother), W. D. Stewart, James Laurie, and George Campbell (no apparent relation); "Campbell's School poems and Translations, 1787-1792;" and clippings (1836). The second commonplace book, "Original Poems by Thomas Campbell," includes Thomas Campbell poems (1788-1840), probably transcribed by William Beattie; unidentified letters to Campbell (1809, 1831); a letter from his nephew Archibald Campbell (1842); letters to Beattie from James Wingate answering requests for copies of Campbell's poems (1846); and clippings.
Series IV, Writings of Others, consists of manuscript copies of poems written by poets other than Thomas Campbell, and is arranged alphabetically by author in folders 30-47. Includes poems by Robert Burns; John Davies; Francis Davison; Thomas Deloney; Henry Dundes; Charles Wyndham, Earl of Egremont; Abraham Fraunce; George Gascoigne; Stephen Hawes; Henry Peacham; James Shirley; Edward Thurlow; Baron Thurlow; Samuel Wesley; Nicholas Whiting; John Wilbye; Charles Harbury Williams; and Anne Finch, Countess of Winchelsea, as well as a few poems by unidentified authors.
Series V, Other Papers, is arranged chronologically in folders 48-49. It includes a summons in the case of "Frederick Campbell Stewart, Esq. of Ascog, against Ferdinand S. Campbell and the other Heirs of Entail to the Estates of Ascog;" and unidentified papers.
English drama -- 18th century; English poetry -- 18th century; Poets, English -- 17th century; Poets, English -- 18th century; Poets, English -- 19th century; Lectures; Poetry; Poets, English; Beattie, William, 1793-1875; Campbell, Ferdinand S.; Campbell, Thomas, 1777-1844; Child, Roylance; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826; Steward, Frederick Campbell; Wingate, James
- Correspondence, Series I
  - Jefferson, Thomas. Manuscript copy of an ALS to Thomas Campbell (1825 Apr 29), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Writings, 1821-39; Series II; 26
  Scope and Contents
  Series II, Writings, is arranged chronologically by date of publication. Unpublished and undated writings are filed after dated writings.
  - Specimens of the British Poets (London: John Murray, 1819)
    - Manuscript draft of Part I of "Essay on English Poetry", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Draft titled "Preface"
    - Manuscript drafts for portions of Part II of "Essay on English Poetry", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Manuscript drafts for portions of Part III of "Essay on English Poetry", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Critical Biographical Notices of the British Poets", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Bound volume containing drafts of biographical essays
      Poets in this volume: Geoffrey Chaucer, Edmund Spencer, John Milton, Abraham Cowley, John Dryden, Alexander Pope, Samuel Butler, John Phillips, Charles Sackville, Earl of Dorset, Thomas Parnell, and Matthew Prior
    - "Critical Biographical Notices of the British Poets", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Poets in this volume: William Cowper, Christopher Anstey, James Beattie, Erasmus Darwin, William Jones, Charlotte Smith, Thomas Warton, Joseph Warton, William Mason, Thomas Chatterton, John Logan, Nathaniel Cotton, William Julius Michle, William Whitehead, Henry Brooke, Soame Jenyns, Richard Jago George Alexander Stevens, Thomas Penrose, Richard Glover, John Langhorne, John Armstrong, Francis Fawkes, George Lord Lyttleton, Thomas Blacklock, Robert Lloyd, and Christopher Smart
    - Papers removed from "Critical Biographical Notices of the British Poets" (folder 6), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Draft biography of Beattie, James, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Draft biography of Burns, Robert, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Draft biography of Cowper, William, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Draft biography of Mason, William, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Draft biography of Warton, Thomas, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "Lectures on Poetry," The New Monthly Magazine (London: Henry Colburn, 1821)
    - "Campbell's Lectures, London- University", 1821 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Printed copy, interleaved into a notebook. Few annotations, primarily page numbers
    - "Portions of the M.S. of Poet Campbell's Lectures on Poetry, A.C.", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Bound volume
  - The Poetical Works of Thomas Campbell. (London: Edward Moxon, Dover Street, 1839)
    - Printed copy interleaved into a notebook with annotations, 1839 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Papers removed from volume, 1839 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - "Lectures on Drama" (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Bound volume of manuscript lectures
  - English history timelines
    - English history timeline, 872-1066, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - English history timeline, 1169-1189, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Research notes, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 20-22)
    Includes notes on the following works: Sharon Turner's The History of the Anglo-Saxons from the Earliest Period to the Norman Conquest, a work on romance by Joseph Ritson, and George Ellis's Specimens of Early English Metrical Romances.
  - Biographies
    - Addison, Joseph, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Hull, Thomas, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Metastasio, Pietro, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Thomson, James, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Unidentified writings, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 27)
    Portion of an essay on "Theory of Beauty" and a fragment
- Commonplace Books, 1846; Series III; 2
  Series III, Commonplace Books, consists of two volumes.
  - "Campbell. Poems.", ca. 1846 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    Includes "Reminiscences of the Poet from January 1837 to June 15 1844 the day of his death, from the diary of Mr. Roylance Child. Transcribed Dec. 1846"; Campbell correspondence (ca. 1795- 1841), including some manuscript copies, consisting of letters to and/or from the following correspondents: Thomas Moore, H. Brougham, Archibald Campbell (b. 1781, brother), Archibald Campbell (nephew), Margaret Campbell (mother), W. D. Stewart, James Laurie, and George Campbell; "Campbell's School poems and Translations, 1787- 1792"; and clippings (1836)
  - "Original Poems by Thomas Campbell", ca. 1846 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    Includes poems (1788-1840), probably transcribed by Dr. William Beattie; unidentified letters to Campbell (1809, 1831), a letter from his nephew, Archibald Campbell (1842); letters to William Beattie from James Wingate answering requests for copies of Campbell's poems (1846); and clippings
- Writings Of Others, n.d.; Series IV; 18
  Series IV, Writings of Others, is arranged alphabetically by author.
  - Burns, Robert, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Davies, John, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Davison, Francis, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Deloney, Thomas, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Dundes, Henry (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Egremont, Charles Wyndham, Earl of (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Fraunce, Abraham, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Gascoigne, George, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Hawes, Stephen, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Peacham, Henry, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Shirley, James, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Thurlow, Edward Thurlow, Baron, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Wesley, Samuel, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Whiting, Nicholas, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Wilbye, John, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Williams, Charles Harbury, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Winchelsea, Anne Finch, Countess of, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Unidentified poets, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 47)
- Other Papers, 1821; Series V; 3
  Series V, Other Papers, is arranged chronologically.
  - Summons, Frederick Campbell Stewart against Ferdinand S. Campbell and others, 1821 Oct (Box 3, Folder 48)
    Full suite name: "Frederick Campbell Stewart, Esq. of Ascog, against Ferdinand S. Campbell and the other Heirs of Entail to the Estates of Ascog." On cover of binding: "Scraps etc.-Campbell-Notes-Mem., 1844"
  - Unidentified papers, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 49)